<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Untitled Document</title>
            <author/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date/>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>no publication statement available</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name/>
            <date/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p rend="start">
            <hi rend="bold">BALCER, Jack Martin</hi>. Born: 9 November 1935, Newark, NJ. Date, Place to father, Father’s occupation, and Mother. Education: B.A. Montclair State College, 1957, M.A. U. of Michigan, 1958; Ph.D., 1964. Married: Prof. Exp.: Asst. prof. hist. Denison U., 1964-65; asst prof hstory, Indiana U., 1965-71; assoc prof. Ohio State, 1971-80; prof. hist., 1980- 2003. Died: 11 July 2004 after a long illness.</p>
         <p rend="start">Jack Balcer enjoyed a long and distinguished ca­reer as a teacher and scholar. As a student at the University of Michigan he worked under the direction of Prof. Paul Alexander. At Denison, Indiana, and Ohio State, he was known as a spell-binding lecturer, and generations of students remember “Dr. B’s” courses as among the highlights of their time at OSU. He brought a quick and lively mind, a keen wit, and genuine enthusiasm for teaching to all of his classes. He was also one of the first here to employ visual aids in virtually all of his classes. An accom­plished photographer, he employed his impressive col­lection of slides of coins, artifacts, and archaeological sites as “texts” to instruct students on how to interpret the past. The University twice recognized the outstand­ing quality of his contribution by the awarding of its highest accolades, the Outstanding Teaching Award (1983) and the Alumni Distinguished Teaching Award (1984). He retired in December of 2003.</p>
         <p rend="start">Jack’s research focused principally on the Athenian Empire, Greek numismatics, the cultural interactions between Greeks and non-Greeks in Western Asia Mi­nor, and on the Persian Empire. His studies led to nu­merous articles and several monographs, among the most important of which are The Athenian Regulations for Chalkis (1978), Sparda by the Bitter Sea (1984), and Herodotus and Bisitun (1987). His scholarly accom­plishments have been recognized by grants awarded by, among others, the American Numismatic Society, the Ford Foundation, the National Endowment for the Hu­manities, the American Council of Learned Societies, and Harvard’s Center for Hellenic Studies.</p>
         <p rend="start">Jack was deeply committed to the University, and served OSU in a variety of capacities during his career here, but his deepest, most abiding passion was for the library. He served for many years on library council, and sought in every way he could to make it the crown jewel of the University.</p>
         <p>DISSERTATION: “From Confederate Freedom to Imperial Tyranny: A Study of the Restrictions Imposed by Athens on the Political Self-Determination of the Member States in the Delian Confederacy, 478-431 B.C.” (Michigan, 1964). </p>
         <p rend="start">PUBLICATIONS: “Peparethos, the Early Coinage Reconsidered,” SNR 46 (1967) 25-33; “The Early Silver Coinage of Teos,” <hi rend="italic">SNR</hi> 47 (1968) 5-50; “Phokaia and Teos. A Monetary Alliance,” <hi rend="italic">SNR</hi> 49 (1970) 25-34; “The Date of Herodotus iv, 1, Darius’ Scythian Expedition,” HSPh 76 (1972) 99-132; “The Mycenaean Dam at Tiryns,” <hi rend="italic">AJA</hi> 78 (1974) 141-49; “Separatism and Anti-Separatism in the Athenian Empire (478-433 B.C.),” <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> 23 (1974) 21-39; “Peparethos. Further Notes,” <hi rend="italic">SNR</hi> 54 (1975) 33-36; “Imperial Magistrates in the Athenian Empire,” <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> 25 (1976) 257-87;<hi rend="italic"> </hi>“The Athenian Episkopos and the Achaemenid « King’s Eye »,” AJP 98 (1977) 252-63; <hi rend="italic">The Athenian Regulations for Chalkis; Studies in the Athenian Imperial Law,</hi> 
            <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> Einzelschr. XXXIII (Wiesbaden : Steiner, 1978) [REVS: Erasmus XXXI 1979 370-372 Germain ; Gnomon LIV 1982 448-453 Moggi]; “The Archaic Coinage of Skyros and the Forgeries of Konstantinos Christodoulos,” <hi rend="italic">SNR</hi> 57 (1978) 69-101; “Alexander’s Burning of Persepolis,” <hi rend="italic">IA</hi> 13 (1978) 119-133; “Imperialism and Stasis in Fifth Century B.C. Ionia. A Frontier Redefined,” in <hi rend="italic">Arktouros. Hellenic Studies Presented to Bernard M. W. Knox on the Occasion of His 65th Birthday, </hi>ed. G.W. Bowersock, W. Burkert &amp; M.C.J. Putnam (Berlin : de Gruyter, 1979) 261-68; “The Greeks and the Persians. The Process of Acculturation,” <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> 32 (1983) 257-67;<hi rend="italic"> Sparda by the Bitter Sea. Imperial Interaction in Western Anatolia</hi> Brown Judaic Stud. ; LII (Chico: Scholars Press, 1984) [REVS: Gnomon LX 1988 544-547 Wiesehoefer]; “Miletos (IG I2.22 [I3.21]) and the Structures of Alliances,” in <hi rend="italic">Studien zum Attischen Seebund</hi> , ed. Balcer et al. (Konstanz: Universitätsverlag, 1984) 11-36 [REVS: Gnomon LVII 1985 657-659 Robertson ; HZ CCXLI 1985 384-386 Kiechle ; CR XXXV 1985 407-408 Steppler ; Gymnasium XCIV 1987 274 Kinzl]; “Fifth Century B.C. Ionia. A Frontier Redefined,” <hi rend="italic">REA</hi> 87 (1985) 31-42; <hi rend="italic">Herodotus and Bisitun; Problems in Ancient Persian Historiography,</hi> 
            <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> Einzelschr. XLIX (Stuttgart: Steiner, 1987) [REVS: CR XXXVIII 1988 434 Stevenson ; RPh LXII 1988 338-340 Menu ; CW LXXXII 1988-1989 455-456 Kawami ; Gnomon LXII 1990 605-609 Wiesehöfer ; Mnemosyne XLIV 1991 469-470 H. T. Wallinga]; “Persian Occupied Thrace (Skudra),” <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> 37 (1988) 1-21; “Ionia and Sparda under the Achaemenid Empire: The Sixth and Fifth Centuries B.C. : Tribute, Taxation and Assessment,” in <hi rend="italic">Le tribut dans l’empire perse : actes de la table ronde de Paris, 12-13 décembre 1986</hi>, ed. Pierre Briant Pierre &amp; Clarisse Herrenschmidt, Travaux de l’Institut d’Études Iraniennes et de l’Université de la Sorbonne Nouvelle 13 (Paris : Louvain Peeters, 1989) 1-27; “The Persian Wars against Greece; A Reassessment,” <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> 38 (1989) 127-43; “The East Greeks under Persian Rule: A Reassessment,” <hi rend="italic">Achaemenid History</hi> VI: <hi rend="italic">Asia Minor and Egypt : Old Cultures in a New Empire: Proceedings of the Groningen 1988 Achaemenid History Workshop</hi>, ed. by Heleen Sancisi-Weerdenburg &amp; Amélie Kuhrt (Leiden: Nederlands Inst. voor het Nabije Oosten, 1991) 57-65; “Herodotus, The «Early State», and Lydia,” <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> 43,2 (1994) 246-249; <hi rend="italic">The Persian Conquest of the Greeks 545-450 B.C.</hi> (Konstanz: Universitäts-Verl. Konstanz, 1995) [REVS: HZ 1997 264 (1) : 149-151 Justus Cobet ; Klio 1999 81 (1) : 232 Josef Wiesehöfer]; “The Liberation of Ionia: 478 B.C.,” <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi> 46,3 (1997) 374-377. </p>
         <p rend="start">SOURCES: <hi rend="italic">APA Newsletter</hi> (October 2004) 26.</p>
         <p rend="start">Nathan Rosenstein</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>